<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jeffburg.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jeffburg.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-04T09:49:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jeffburg.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jeffrey Bergier</title><subtitle>A software developer and tech lover trying to share his enthusiasm</subtitle><entry><title type="html">WaterMe: Gardening Reminders</title><link href="https://jeffburg.com/apps/2016/04/15/WaterMe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WaterMe: Gardening Reminders" /><published>2016-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeffburg.com/apps/2016/04/15/WaterMe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeffburg.com/apps/2016/04/15/WaterMe.html"><![CDATA[<p>WaterMe was my first app that was 100% a CRUD app. CRUD basically means that its
a database app. It Creates, Reads, Updates, and Deletes database entries. But it
displays them in a nice way with really great animations. The premise of the app
is that, unlike reminders style apps, this app only gives you one reminder per
day letting you know which plants need to be watered that day.</p>

<p>Because of this premise, I had to do quite a lot of complex date math to figure
out which day a plant need to be watered. If your a developer, you know this can
be complex because days and time zones are pretty complex. As well, because I
don’t use a Push Notification server, I need to schedule what Apple calls “Local
Notifications,” This basically means that any time the database changes, I need
to look about 14 days ahead and figure out, for every day, if a plant needs to
be watered and which one, and then schedule 14 notifications. Anyway, I am going
too deep.</p>

<p>WaterMe has been on the app store since 2016 and has gone through many updates
and changes to improve as new features are added into the OS, such as drag and
drop which you can see in the screenshot to the left. Over the years I also
enable Core Data to CloudKit syncing for automatic and reliable iCloud sync
between devices.</p>

<p>include embed/video.html src=’{/assets/img/apps-waterme/apps-video-waterme.mp4}’</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Apps" /><category term="cocoa" /><category term="cocoa-touch" /><category term="swift" /><category term="uikit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[WaterMe was my first app that was 100% a CRUD app and has been on the App Store since 2016.]]></summary></entry></feed>